This is Yuki Hamura from the drama department.
這位是戲劇部門的羽村由貴
We joined the company in the same year.
我們同期進公司
What's the matter? Did you have an affair?
怎麼了？搞外遇了嗎？
That's rude.
太失禮了啦
Come on, who hasn't had an affair or two?
外遇這種小事大家都在做啦
Affairs were all the rage in Showa 60.
昭和60年的外遇潮很不得了喔
Even Eiji Bando was popular.
就連板東英二都有異性緣
Haven't you heard of Kintsuma?
你們沒聽過 《給星期五的妻子們》嗎？
D-Don't worry.
別擔心
In the end, he'll be really empathetic.
他聽過後一定會親切地幫你
Starting this spring, she's teaming up with a big-shot scriptwriter
她從春天開始要跟大牌編劇 一起製作連續劇
Have you heard of Kentaro Emo?
你知道江面賢太郎先生嗎？
The only screenwriter I know is James Miki.
編劇我只認識詹姆斯三木
From the late 90s to the early 2000s,
從1990年代後期到2000年初期
he was the leading writer who had massive support from the youth.
他受到廣大年輕人的支持 可以說是時代先驅
He's famous for An Eye for an Eye and…
代表作為《以眼還眼》…
Love for My Brother.
《以愛還兄》
Oh, yeah! Back in high school, everyone was hooked on it.
就是那部！高中時代大家都有看
That iconic scene in the broadcast room.
最知名的就是廣播室的那一幕
"I can't return your love, because I…"
“老師無法回應你的愛，因為我…”
And then, Haruka, the protagonist, realizes the mic is on.
當他說出這句話時 主角的春香注意到麥克風被打開了
Exactly, she realizes the mic is on!
對，她注意到了！
Haruka freaks out and pushes the teacher down.
然後春香急忙推倒老師
But then the teacher drops the bomb.
但是老師仍說出口了
"Because I'm your brother."
“因為我是你的哥哥”
And it's broadcast to the whole school!
那段話就在全校廣播裡播了出來
Every student in the school hears it.
所以全校學生都聽到了
Then, in the gym, someone shoots a basketball,
這時體育館有人在投籃
and it shifts to slow motion, but the ball…
球以慢鏡頭投向籃框…
misses.
但是沒進
It misses! That was a metaphor, wasn't it?
球沒有進！那是一種隱喻吧？
He was the wizard of metaphors!
他還被稱作是“隱喻魔法師”呢！
You're not impressed?
奇怪，你沒興趣嗎？
No. That's not true. I'm enjoying this.
怎麼會，我聽著覺得很有趣喔
Oh, speaking of Emoken,
還有啊，說到江賢
there was a drama about a street gang in Shimbashi?
就會聯想到新橋街頭幫派的那部吧？
SSLP, Shimbashi SL Park.
簡稱是SSLP的《新橋SL公園》
We used to copy the SL boys' fashion!
你也模仿過SL男孩的穿衣風格吧？
What was the iconic line from the protagonist again?
主角的經典台詞是什麼來著？
"That's so neutral!"
“無關痛癢！”
Not many chances to drop that line these days.
很少有機會用到這句呢
I know, right?
對啊
Sorry for leaving you hanging.
抱歉，把你晾在一旁
No worries. Don't mind me.
沒關係，我不介意
Anyway, he's like the embodiment of my youth.
總之他代表著我的青春
I've always dreamt of working with him in this industry,
既然從事這行，就希望有一天能合作
but it was impossible!
但是我不能見他！
I didn't want to risk seeming like a cringy fan.
我太喜歡他了 不想被當作是瘋狂粉絲
So your dream finally came true.
那你的夢想實現了呢
Yes. We had a meeting today.
對，今天有見面開會
As it turns out…
從結論來說…
I wish I never met him.
早知道就別見他了
It's been so long since I've visited EBS. What was my last project?
我好久沒來EBS了 上次是什麼時候？
Love Navigation in 2003.
自2003年的《愛情導航》
LN, huh?
《愛導》啊？
You guys probably don't know me.
那你們肯定不認識我
I bet you weren't even born.
不如說你們還沒出生吧
Anyway, it's an honor to collaborate with…
總之這次我們有幸
I have a fun story about the LN wrap-up party.
-參與企劃… -《愛導》的慶功宴上有件趣事
We were at an Italian place in Roppongi, and I had a little spat with Johnny.
我在六本木的義大利餐館 和強尼有點摩擦
You know him as Giba now.
強尼現在是叫阿柳
And Show Aikawa ended up stopping us.
結果是哀川翔勸架
As we were leaving, the bill was already settled.
等我們要離開店裡 才發現已經有人買單了
Guess who covered it.
猜猜是誰結帳的？
-What do you call it, idle talk? -Mariko Kaga.
-那算是閒聊嗎？ -是加賀真理子
He kept on bragging for nearly two hours.
他自吹自擂了將近兩小時
And it was all…
而且總覺得那些內容…
-Is it behind the times? -Exactly.
-很過時 -對
He was totally dwelling on the past in his choice of words and topics.
話題或用詞都很有年代感，然後呢…
What inspired me to join this industry was your Eye for an Eye and…
我會以進入這行為目標 契機就是因為你寫的《以眼還眼》…
I can't stand people who dwell on the past.
我討厭舊事重提的人
Right. I'm sorry.
我想也是，抱歉
There are sexual services for women, right?
話說不是有女性專用風俗店嗎？
Huh?
什麼？
An ordinary housewife stumbles upon sexual services for women by chance.
因為一些偶然的原因 平凡的主婦得知女性風俗店的存在
But then her daughter finds out by chance.
但偶然被女兒發現
That's from LN, right?
那不就是《愛導》的內容嗎？
In the third episode of LN…
我記得《愛導》的第三集…
I was amazed at how ahead of the times you were.
不愧是時代先驅，太令人驚訝了
-I remember so-- -How about a shared house?
-所以我記得很清楚… -分租公寓這主題怎麼樣？
A bookstore owner and an actress meet by chance
書店店員和女演員偶然相遇
and end up living together by chance.
因為偶然的狀況而同居
So come up with those chance scenarios!
告訴我那個“偶然”是什麼啊！
As a screenwriter, it's his job!
作家才要負責構思 那個偶然的內容吧！
Wait, an actress and a bookstore owner?
等等，要讓女演員 跟書店男生當主角？
Yup, it's totally from Notting Hill.
跟《新娘百分百》一模一樣
Yikes.
太扯了吧
Why is he like this?
怎麼會變成這樣？
The truth is, Mr. Emo announced a hiatus in 2008.
其實江面先生在2008年 就宣布要停筆了
Let's delve into what Emoken has been up to during his break.
徹底解說停筆的江賢過著怎樣的生活
He suddenly developed a passion for environmental issues,
他突然開始關心環境問題
relocated to Okinawa, and started blogging about ecology and slow living.
搬到沖繩去，開始在部落格上 發表有關生態和慢活的文章
In his personal life, he abruptly married a model 19 years his junior,
在私生活則是 和小他19歲的模特兒閃電結婚
but they split 18 months later.
但一年半就離婚了
He raised funds through crowdfunding to open a salon, but it closed.
接著又透過群眾募資籌錢 線上沙龍開了又關
Lately, he's been sharing about his relationship
最近於公於私都表示
with an influencer 19 years his junior.
自己和小他19歲的網紅感情很好
Apart from his romantic history, everything he does is inconsistent.
除了戀愛方面以外 都沒什麼固定的方向性呢
In fact, the higher-ups are saying he can't attract enough viewers anymore.
其實上頭也認定 現在找江賢來收視率也不會多高
I bet it's tough for him to admit he's old news now.
他不想承認自己已經過氣了吧
Which makes it hard for me to work with him.
所以我們也很難指出這點
Why don't I tell him?
由我來跟他說如何？
Huh?
什麼？
Tell him what?
你要說什麼？
"Stop sharing old stories. They're outdated and bothering everyone."
“別再聊往事 早就已經過時了，大家很困擾”
Please don't.
不好吧…
Someone older should tell him.
由年紀大的人來講這種事是最好的
When's your next meeting?
下次會議是什麼時候？
Wednesday, from 4 p.m.
這個星期三，下午四點開始
I happen to be free.
我剛好有空
Hey.
我問你
Are you okay?
你沒問題吧？
What do you mean?
幹嘛這樣問？
Nothing.
沒什麼
This man is Mr. Ichiro Ogawa, EBS TV's counselor.
他是EBS電視台的專屬諮商師 小川市郎先生
He was my grandfather on my late mother's side.
其實是我過世的外公
Say, Kiyoshi,
阿清，你啊
how long are you staying here?
會在這裡待到什麼時候？
I don't know. I've got to ask Mom.
不曉得，得問我媽
No.
不會
She's a sociologist, right?
她是社會學者對吧？
Eiji Okuda is about to have an affair with Ryoko Moriyama.
奧田瑛二好像快和森山良子外遇了
Ryoko Moriyama and Tomoko Ogawa are best friends.
森山良子和小川知子是好朋友
It's unsettling.
感覺有些風吹草動
What's with Eiji Okuda's sexiness?
奧田瑛二怎麼會如此性感？
I didn't get it as a child but now I do.
小時候看還沒什麼感覺
Anyone would get the butterflies.
即使一開始沒那麼想 如今再看會不禁滿面春風
And…
而且…
I love this person more than anything in the world.
我在世上最喜歡這個人了
Eiji Bando's likability just skyrocketed.
對板東英二的好感度會暴增
A child is happiest when their parents get along.
要是父母相處得融洽 對孩子而言就是最幸福的了
And parents are happiest
孩子之間相處得融洽
when children get along.
對父母而言就是最幸福的了
-This is such a tearjerker. -So who cares what other people say?
-這種劇情會讓人哭出來啦 -何必在乎他人？
Your dad loves your mom.
爸爸最愛媽媽了
A whole lot.
最愛她了
Welcome back.
你們回來啦
What?
幹嘛？
Junko wants to know how long we're staying.
純子學姐問說我們會待到什麼時候
As long as Kintsuma is running.
待到《給星期五的妻子們》演完
That's a rerun.
那是重播喔
Kiyoshi doesn't want to go back.
是因為阿清不想回去
Dinner isn't ready yet.
晚飯還沒好喔
What?
怎麼了？
Has there been any word?
他有聯絡你嗎？
From your father?
你爸爸？
Not today.
今天沒有
Not today? So, not today either.
今天沒有？是今天“也”沒有
Is he really in the future?
那傢伙真的跑到未來了嗎？
Maybe he's playing elsewhere.
不會是跑去哪玩了吧？
Hey, be quiet!
安靜點！
Can we read one more? We can?
能夠再唸一張嗎？可以嗎？
Okay, the handle is Mysterious Transfer Student.
好，筆名是神祕轉學生
-No way. -That's me!
-不會吧 -唸到我的了！
Hanky-panky apple.
今天做了嗎？
"There's a student in my class I haven't met yet."
“班上有個我沒見過的同學
"It seems he hasn't come to school since I transferred."
聽說從我轉學來之前就沒來上學
"And he won't answer the phone."
-電話也不接” -我的天哪…
"Hey, S."
“喂，S同學”
"If you peek under your TV's cathode ray tube,
-我是神祕轉學生 -“如果從電視映像管由下往上看
you might be able to see Iyo's pants."
搞不好會看到伊代的內褲喔”
This kid is so silly!
這傢伙真蠢！
I'm from Class B, Grade 3 at School 6--
我是第六國中3年B班的…
The Mysterious Transfer Student.
神祕轉學生
I'm sorry. He doesn't want to see anyone.
對不起，他說不想見你們
Mysterious Transfer Student, you've won a present.
我要送神祕轉學生 劇本統籌江賢的個人物品
Writer Emoken's personal sunglasses.
一副墨鏡
-Shall we head back? -You might not want them.
-回家吧 -但沒人想要吧
Sunglasses were fine,
墨鏡倒還好
but he kept giving away my stuff like my wristwatch and sneakers.
對方後來開始會送些私人物品 像是手錶跟球鞋
It was such a pain.
真讓人受不了
Everyone has interesting pasts, huh? How about we start discussing--
每個人都有一段歷史呢 那差不多該討論企劃了…
Zucchi took really good care of me.
我當時受到阿木先生的照顧呢
Do you guys know Be Early or There Will Be Hanky-Panky?
你們沒聽過這節目吧？ 《不早做的夜晚會做那檔子事》
It was a program that would never fly compliance-wise today.
若是現在播會不合乎規範，完全出局
It's not Be Early, it's Go to Bed Early or There Will Be Hanky-Panky.
不是“不早做”，是“不早睡” 《不早睡的夜晚會做那檔子事》
Who?
你是誰？
Someone gets what I'm talking about.
這不是有聊得來的人嗎？
This is our company's counselor, Mr. Ogawa.
這位是公司的專屬諮商師小川先生
I've been to a public filming of Hanky-Panky.
我有去看 《不早睡那檔事》的公開錄製
Have you heard of the drama featuring the Hanky-Panky girls?
那做那檔子事女孩主演的連續劇是？
Hanky-Panky on Friday, and More Hanky-Panky on Saturday.
《週五要做那檔子事 週六要做更多那檔子事》
No way, that's my debut piece!
不會吧，那可是我的出道作品！
Wow. It's not even on Wikipedia.
好厲害，就連維基百科都沒寫耶
What are you, a Showa geek?
你是昭和迷嗎？
You can ask me anything up until Showa 61.
到昭和61年前為止的事 你什麼都能問
I'll take it from here. Everyone, back to your jobs.
這邊交給我吧，大家先回去工作
Or head home if you can.
能回家的就先回去吧
Good work.
辛苦了
Let me tell you, that drama was such a pain to make.
我跟你說喔，拍那部劇可累人了
The other lead was such a poor actor we had to pull in--
對手演員的演技有夠差，臨時找人…
Toshinori Omi.
尾美利德
Exactly, Omi accepted the role.
沒錯，是找尾美演的
-And the theme song was… -Senri Oe.
-主題曲是… -大江千里
Senri Oe, exactly!
大江千里，對！
No, it was Omega Tribe.
不對，是Omega Tribe
Wait, you know more than I do.
等等，竟然比我還清楚
Let's grab drinks in Kasumicho.
我們去霞町喝一杯吧
You were late. How many bars did you hit up?
回來得真晚，喝了幾家呀？
Three.
三家
I had a blast myself talking about the good old days.
我漸漸覺得懷念，不小心就大聊特聊
Did it make you want to return?
會讓你想回去嗎？
To Showa?
回昭和？
I can't.
沒辦法啦
I'm too busy, thanks to you guys.
多虧你們，讓我忙了起來
I'm going to be on TV.
我下次要上電視呢
Wait, you two know each other?
什麼嘛，原來你們兩人認識？
That'll save us time.
那就好談了
I was just looking for a participant.
我剛好在找回答者
Mr. Kazushige Nagashima keeps going away to Hawaii.
長嶋一茂先生動不動就會跑去夏威夷
What do you say?
要不要考慮一下？
A general knowledge quiz?
“常識問答”？
Me? You can't pick me.
我去上節目？不行吧
Everything I say is inappropriate.
我一開口就很不妥喔
That's why you're perfect.
就是這樣才好啊
TV is so dull these days.
現在的節目很無聊
Everyone's so neutral.
都是些無關痛癢的內容
Don't you agree, Uryu?
對吧？瓜生
You
你啊
should be on this.
就上節目吧
So, I'll be staying here for a while.
因此我暫時要待在這邊
Don't you miss your daughter, Junko?
你不想見純子嗎？
Sorry. Maybe I should've put Ms.
抱歉，我不該叫得這麼親密
If I see her, I might let my emotions show.
要是見面，我就會表現在臉上
I'm like an open book.
我這人很好懂
Is it already showing?
根本已經寫在臉上了吧？
Yeah.
也是啦
I bet it would distress Junko as well
要是聽到“九年後我跟你都會死掉”
if I told her, "In nine years, you and I are going to die."
會害純子感到困擾吧
I'm going to bed.
我去睡了
MR. OGAWA
（小川老師）
Found it.
有了
CALLING
（小川老師 撥號中）
SAKAE
（紗加惠小姐）
MR. OGAWA
（小川老師）
This is stupid.
我真蠢
Let go of me!
放開我…
What is this place? What university?
這是哪裡？什麼大學？
The lab of the Metropolis Institute of Technology.
首都工業大學理工學系的實驗室
Please go see Junko.
請你去純子小姐身邊吧
What?
什麼？
Um…
那個…
I mean…
總覺得好像…
It just feels like
雖然不太清楚
you're like, you know,
但市郎先生你好像…
running from like, some kind of problem.
好像是在逃避面對某件事
You use "like" a lot.
你講了好多個“好像”
If I were a parent, I'd want to spend as much time as possible with my kid.
如果我是父親，會想多跟女兒相處
What would I do if I saw her?
見到了又該怎麼做？
I can't tell her the truth.
這些現實我說不出口啊
Why not?
說出來不就好了？
What good will that do? I can't change the future!
說了又能怎樣？未來是不能改變的！
Why can't you?
改變不就好了？
You can't do that.
那就麻煩了
Since I arrived early,
我提早到了
I asked him to give me a tour and explain the principle of the time machine.
他替我介紹內部 我順便請教他時光機的原理
I'm not concerned with the specifics.
我並不想聽你的說詞
Just transport Ichiro to the past.
請將市郎先生送回過去
Forget it. I don't want to go.
不用啦，我不想搭
This project has government recognition,
雖然政府認可了這項計畫
but trial runs are currently being conducted in secret.
但就現階段而言 是在祕密進行測試運行
Only one bus runs on Saturday.
只有星期六的一班車
Saturday?
星期六？
It leaves at 4:55 a.m. and returns at 3:55 p.m.
去程是清晨4點55分 回程是下午3點55分
My son added the times to the timetable to remember them,
我兒子怕忘記就將時間寫在時刻表上
and he hid it with tape.
再用膠帶蓋住
Currently,
目前呢
there are 50 passengers, including my wife and son,
包括我妻子在內 能搭乘的人只有50名
registered on a face recognition system.
我已經事先在人臉辨識系統 登錄了他們的資料
What? Then why was I able to board the bus?
什麼？那我為什麼能搭？
That's because…
那是因為啊…
when setting up the facial recognition system,
在建構臉部認證系統時
I used your photo as a sample.
我使用了老師的照片當作測試的範本
That's creepy.
好噁心
I was born with weak semicircular canals,
我天生三半規管就不好
That's why I switched to a self-driving bus.
因此便換成了自動駕駛
That explains the other passengers.
所以才會有其他乘客上車啊
Any other questions?
有其他問題嗎？
That's because…
那是因為…
I don't know.
我不曉得
Why don't you know that?
為什麼就只有那點不知道啦？
Did you know…
你早就知道了嗎？
that I'm going to die?
知道我過世的事
Of course.
當然
I visit your grave every year.
我每年都會去掃墓
I'm in a grave, huh?
原來我在墳墓裡啊？
You should've said, baldy.
早點說啊，禿子
What if you stop Junko from meeting the black suit at a disco…
如果讓純子小姐 不要遇到迪斯可的黑衣領班…
No way.
那可不行
Why not? Both you and Junko will be able to live.
為什麼？這樣就能拯救 純子小姐和市郎先生了
Nagisacchi wouldn't exist!
那小渚就不會出生了！
It's inevitable. It can't be helped.
這都是必然的，沒辦法
Dying isn't a negative event.
死亡不是一件消極的事
Rather, having the chance to meet you as an adult is a positive experience.
因為能像這樣見到長大後的小渚 反而是好事
I'm already dead, after all.
因為我其實已經死了
Grandpa…
外公…
I guess I'll go see your mom after so long.
那我就久違地去見你媽媽吧
Crap.
糟糕…
Kiyoshi, wait!
阿清，等一下！
You forgot your rice balls!
你忘記拿飯糰了！
Hey!
等等！
-Good morning.
-早安
-Morning.
-早啊 -早安
I spotted Yuki Matsumura at a station in Kinshicho!
我今天在錦糸町站前 看到松村雄基了！
No way! The Baddest Punk in Kawahama?
不會吧！川濱第一的不良少年？
Why was he there?
為什麼？
He's probably shooting a new drama.
我猜是新戲的外景吧
Skip school?
要蹺課嗎？
Definitely!
就決定蹺課了！
-Yeah.
-好耶
Junko.
純子
You're back.
你回來啦
Where did you get that?
那身打扮是怎樣？
It's custom-made.
是我訂製的
What do you think?
好看嗎？
Pretty cool.
滿不錯的嘛
Junko.
純子
Yeah.
嗯
I'm back.
我回來了
I'm back, Junko.
我回來了，純子
-Yeah.
-嗯
Hey, my friends are watching.
我說啊，朋友都在看啦
Take good care of Junko.
就拜託你們多多關照純子了
Oh, okay.
哦，好的
Too tight.
好大力
Mr. Ogawa?
小川老師？
What are you doing?
你在做什麼？
Sakae.
紗加惠小姐
Thanks for looking after things while I was gone.
謝謝你在我不在時幫忙看家
Whoa, hey!
哇，幹嘛？
Stop. It's too early for that.
一大早的，請你別這樣
What?!
怎麼了啊？
Mr. Ogawa, where have you been?
老師，你是去了哪裡？
Just somewhere else.
說來話長
-Mr. Principal! -What?
-校長，你看這個！ -什麼？
Check this out.
這很猛喔
-You wear it like this. -What? No.
-像這樣戴著 -什麼？不要啦
There you go.
給你吧
Huh? Hey.
什麼？喂
-What's this? -You've caused us trouble.
-這什麼啊？ -你這樣讓人很困擾
Even as an assistant, you can't just be absent without--
雖說你是副班導，但持續無故曠職…
Now, Mr. Yasumori, you're a Hanshin fan, aren't you?
別生氣了，安森老師 你是阪神的球迷吧？
This is an Okada mug commemorating their victory after 38 years.
這是睽違38年的優勝紀念 岡田的馬克杯
After 38 years?
-38年？ -對
What do you mean, 38 years?
睽違38年是什麼意思？
What is this?
這是什麼東西？
Women! I see women!
女人！這裡有女人！
Huh?
怎麼回事？
Eat up. Eat more, Junko!
吃吧，你盡量吃，純子
I feel a little bad for joining you for dinner.
不好意思啊，連我也讓你請客
We're going to have a lot to do with each other ahead.
我們之後會有緣相處一陣子
Right.
這樣啊
Is that so?
真的假的？
Maybe you're my future husband.
可能是我未來的老公呢
Huh? Is he really?
什麼？真的是這樣嗎？
Never mind. Just eat.
別管了，快吃吧，純子
Forget the leeks. Eat the meat two slices at a time!
別吃蔥了，一次吃兩片肉吧
Do people in the future eat sukiyaki too?
未來人也會吃壽喜燒啊？
We mostly eat the same stuff.
食物都差不多
The saury gets smaller, though.
但秋刀魚會變小
Hmm.
是喔
What's with the "hmm."
你那是什麼反應？
Something seems off.
感覺好可疑
You didn't go to the future, did you?
你其實沒去未來吧？
Sorry.
不好意思
I've been feeling like I'm not keeping up.
我從剛才就覺得自己被晾在一旁
With what?
什麼意思？
With the conversation about the future and stuff.
你們的話題我聽不懂 說什麼未來怎麼樣
Should I take all of this with a grain of salt?
我是不是隨意聽聽就好啊？
How about another egg?
我再幫你加顆蛋吧
Yes, please.
麻煩你了
You were in Susukino, weren't you?
你其實沒去未來，而是去了薄野吧？
Junko!
純子！
I can explain. I had a spat with my wife in the past.
你誤會了，我以前跟太太吵架
When Junko was still a kid, she had a fever and was crying.
純子還小的時候發燒大哭
But I was sitting there, watching an 11 PM special on Susukino.
我坐在那邊看“11PM”的薄野特輯
And I failed to notice.
沒注意到異狀
I'm surprised you remember.
你記得真清楚
Don't dodge the question.
別講些以前的事糊弄過去
You're lying to me.
你在騙我吧？
Do you have any proof?
證據呢？
Tell us something surprising about the future,
你要是真的去了就說些 會讓我們嚇到的未來話題吧
Tell me what it's like 38 years down the road.
告訴我38年後的世界會變成什麼樣子
Junko Mihara becomes a Diet member.
三原順子會成為國會議員
What?!
什麼？
That's a lie!
你在騙人！
It's true. She's an active politician.
沒騙你，她是很活躍的政治家
You expect us to believe that?
怎麼可能
She's Reiko Yamada, the queen of hussies, our role model.
她可是我們的憧憬 不良少女的始祖山田麗子耶
She's famous for saying, "Not the face, focus on his body."
那個叫人別打臉 要打身體的山田麗子
And she's in politics now? Unbelievable.
竟然變成政治家？怎麼可能
She's confusing reality with Mr. Kinpachi.
你把現實跟《金八老師》的 世界線混為一談了
I've got one more.
還有一件事
You'll be astonished.
你聽了肯定會超驚訝
Kato-chan
加藤茶他啊
at the age of 80, has a wife who's 35.
都80歲了，卻有個35歲的太太
What?!
什麼？
Are you kidding me?
那是怎樣？
If his wife is 35 in 38 years,
38年後是35歲
she hasn't even been born!
那現在不就還沒出生嗎？
That's scary! It's like a sci-fi story!
討厭！好可怕，太科幻了！
Kin-chan is 82.
阿欽82歲
He drops out of university when he's 78.
78歲的時候從大學休學
Stop. The fabric of time and space…
別說了，時空…
It's unraveling!
時空要扭曲了！
What about Matchy? Our idol?
阿真呢？我們的阿真怎麼樣了？
After a series of events, he becomes a racer.
發生了很多事，最後成了賽車手
That's our Matchy!
真不愧是他！
I'm sorry.
抱歉啊
I don't know what to say.
我不知道該說什麼
I don't care about myself.
我是沒關係啦
I can die whenever.
什麼時候死了都沒差
But not Junko.
但純子就不同了
To think she only has 26 years to live.
竟然26歲就過世了
It's too short.
再怎麼說
No matter how you look at it.
這也太早了
Totally.
就是說啊
My wife was often sick,
因為我太太身體不好
so I took special care of Junko's health.
所以我養女兒時 對她的身體健康特別費心
But all that effort will be wasted. Damn it.
這不是全都白費了嗎？可惡
If you know how your life will play out,
知道以後會怎麼發展的人生
is there even a point in living?
有必要過下去嗎？
It can't be helped.
沒辦法
Not this.
對此我們無能為力
Sorry.
抱歉
You're about the only one I can talk to.
除了你之外，我沒人可以訴苦
So…
所以…
what are you going to do?
你要怎麼做？
What would you do?
如果是你會怎麼做？
If you knew that your son only had nine years left to live,
當你知道兒子只能再活九年
would you tell him?
你會跟他說嗎？
If there's no way to change his fate, there's no use in telling him.
如果是無法改變的命運 那說了也無濟於事
That would be my line of thinking, I think.
我會這樣想吧
Is it really inevitable?
真的無法改變未來嗎？
Up to the point that Nagisa is born,
直到小渚出生
Junko's life isn't bad.
純子的人生都過得還不錯
It's wonderful, in fact.
甚至可以說是好極了
We're all smiles,
不管是純子或是我
Junko and I.
都笑著呢
The problem is what comes next.
但這之後才是問題
I know…
在這之後…
what happens after this.
我知道會發生什麼事
And yet, I can't…
明明知道，不過我卻…
Maybe you're supposed to worry about it
這種事情就是要等時候到了
when that moment comes.
再來想吧
If the situation will stay the same
如果現在思考
whether you fret about it now or later,
跟到時再思考都不會有多大的差別
maybe it's best to enjoy the present
現在就好好享受日子
and live life the way you want to.
隨心所欲地生活如何？
You're right.
也對
It's not happening right away.
這又不是馬上就會發生的事
We still have nine years ahead of us.
我們還有九年呢
Nine years left to live.
還能活九年
You…
你…
You were here?
你原來在啊？
Why did you think I was gone?
為何以為我不在啦？
Quiet! Come over here.
安靜點！過來
My stomach hurt because I ate too much.
我肚子痛，因為吃太多了
So, I was using the bathroom
所以跑去廁所
when you guys, like, started this serious conversation.
結果好像聽到你們在講不得了的事情
And it was like, I didn't even exist,
好像我根本不存在一樣
and I couldn't like, step out.
想出來但好像又出不來
You sure use "like" a lot.
你也很愛說“好像”呢
I'm not the type of guy to leave without a word.
我又不是會一聲不吭就回家的人
I always make sure to say thank you before I leave.
離開前我會好好說“今天打擾了”
-I've got decency. -Sorry about that.
-雖然我看起來很壞，但也懂得禮貌 -抱歉啦
Take care on your way home.
回家路上小心
Hey.
等一下
Is Junko going to die?
純子會死嗎？
Let's step outside.
到外面去談吧
Come on.
來吧…
What's going on? Is something the matter?
幹嘛啊？怎麼了？
Huh?
什麼？
Nothing. Go back to sleep.
沒事啦，快睡吧
-Junko. Is Junko going to die? -Listen, Akitsu. Hey!
-純子，純子會死嗎？ -秋津，別激動！
Calm down. Listen to me.
冷靜點，聽我說
That was
那其實啊
all an act.
是在演戲
An act?
演戲？
Yes, just an act.
對，就是演戲
We lied for you to hear,
為了讓你變成真男人
to make a man out of you.
所以我們故意 以讓你聽得到的音量撒謊
To make
都是為了讓我變成真男人？
That's right.
對
Junko is experiencing the frogification phenomenon right now.
純子現在對你產生蛙化現象
Junko is turning into a frog?
純子變成青蛙？
It's when you lose interest in your crush
當一直以來單戀的對象 突然注意起自己
Girls are like that.
女生都是這樣
So,
所以說啊
it's best to distance yourself for now
你現在就先暫時拉開距離
and make her feel anxious.
讓她感到不安吧
I don't…
那種事…
dislike doing that sort of thing.
我不討厭喔
-Good. -Yeah.
-太好了 -對啊
-Hey. -Huh?
-我問你 -嗯？
How was Yasuko Sawaguchi?
澤口靖子變得怎樣了？
She was working for S.R.I.
她在科搜研工作
What about Yuki Saito?
齊藤由貴呢？
She was in the investigation division.
在搜查一課工作
The delinquent detective?
當飛女刑事嗎？
Cool.
好厲害
What about me?
那我呢？
What?
什麼？
Never mind. I don't want to know.
算了，我不想聽
I want to keep it a surprise.
不然樂趣就減半了
Goodnight.
晚安
CAFE &amp; BAR SCANDAL
（緋聞咖啡廳、酒吧）
She's excited about the future.
她很期待啊
Now, I really can't tell her.
更讓人說不出口了
It's Thursday.
星期四啊
Still two days to go.
還有兩天
Even though I'm finally back home,
好不容易回來了
the week feels unbearably long.
卻覺得一週好漫長
Give me one.
給我一根
Here.
來
-Barkeep. -Huh?
-老闆 -幹嘛？
How much longer will you run this place?
這間店你打算再開幾年？
Five years at most, I think.
五年就差不多了吧
Why?
為什麼？
It's about time. The customers are dwindling, after all.
時候到了，客人也變少了
Things were at their peak around the time of the Tokyo Olympics.
東京奧運那時候生意最好
1964.
1964年
I went to catch the events.
我也去看了呢
I was so bummed seeing Abebe wearing shoes.
還因為看到阿比比穿了鞋而失望呢
Crap. My daughter is going to scold me again.
糟糕，我女兒又要生氣了
Junko?
純子嗎？
She always says, "Don't dwell on the past!"
她叫我不要一直話當年
I wonder why.
為什麼會這樣呢？
Reminiscing is easier.
這樣才輕鬆嘛
Talking about the future at our age brings us down.
都這個年紀了還在思考未來 只會變得難受
When geezers can't find hope in the future,
如果無法對未來抱持希望
they start reminiscing about the past.
老頭就只好說些陳年往事
Junko is just getting started.
純子的人生現在才要開始
She has a brilliant future ahead of her.
還有燦爛的未來在等著她
What's not to envy?
真羨慕她
Hey!
喂！
Wake up, ugly!
該起床了，醜女！
Get out of bed, you little!
你這混蛋是要睡到幾點？
Shut up.
吵死了
Don't barge in, you short gorilla!
別擅自跑進來，矮子大猩猩
If I'm a short gorilla, that makes you an ugly gorilla!
我若是矮子大猩猩 那你這女兒就是醜女大猩猩
Junko, what's your plan for today?
純子，今天有什麼計畫？
Huh? School.
幹嘛？就去上學啊
It's Saturday, so it's a half-day, right?
今天星期六，是“半假”吧？
Just say "after school."
說“放學後”啦
Come with me. I've got something to show you.
陪我一下，我有東西想給你看
We're catching the 3:55 p.m. bus,
我們要搭3點55分的公車
so meet me at School-6-ura bus stop ten minutes beforehand.
所以提早十分鐘在六中裏公車站集合
Huh?
什麼？
Mr. Ogawa…
小川老師…
No way, you're creeping me out. What do you want to show me?
我才不要去，你要幹嘛？ 說什麼有東西要給我看，真噁心
Go, Junko. You should go.
去吧，純子，去一趟比較好
SCHOOL-6-URA
（六中裏 往工大正門前）
Take care, Junko.
路上小心，純子
Watch out for touts, themed cafes, and owing hosts.
特別留意街頭拉客、概念咖啡廳 千萬別跟男公關賒帳
What? I didn't get any of that.
什麼？我完全聽不懂
Where are we going?
要去哪？
Come on.
來
Hey.
喂
What are you doing?
你在幹嘛？
You should, too. Your ears will go "eeee."
你也照做，不然耳朵會嗡嗡作響
We are stopping at Shiga Icchome.
停靠志賀一丁目
All right.
好
What do you think?
怎麼樣？
What do you mean?
什麼怎麼樣？
It's nothing special.
哪有什麼特別的
Look at that.
你看
What the hell is that?
那是什麼？
It's the Skytree.
是晴空塔
She has something dangling from her ears.
有東西從她耳朵裡垂下來耶
That person and that person too.
那些人也是
They're called AirPods.
那是AirPods
They're showing their tummies.
那女生肚子露了出來
So slim! Their waists are so slim.
好瘦！肚子好平坦
Thanks for going up there.
拜託你了
Can I get on now?
我踩上去囉
I'll keep it steady.
我會好好壓著的
Yes, thank you.
好，麻煩你了
Junko, these people…
純子，這些人啊…
have taken good care of me here in this world.
當爸爸在這邊的世界時 受了他們很多的照顧
I'm Nagisa Inushima.
我是犬島渚
Cool name.
真棒的名字
From "Nagisa no Haikara Ningyo"?
是從《沙灘上的摩登人魚》取的嗎？
Yeah.
沒錯
This man is my father.
這位是我父親
Come on, Dad.
真是的，爸爸
Stop crying. You're scaring Junko.
你別哭啦，純子會怕
Your father has told me about you.
我聽你爸說了
Junko the hussy.
你就是大姐頭的純子
What?
什麼？
You want me to kill you?
你少胡說，小心我幹掉你
You really are a hussy!
真的是大姐頭耶！
Is it seriously 2024 now?
現在真的是2024年？
This isn't a prank?
不是什麼整人拍攝？
It's not. This is Reiwa 6.
不是，現在是令和6年
Look at the barkeep.
你看老闆
He's doddering.
他都老成那樣了
Mutchy?
阿睦學長？
That's my dad.
他是我爸
I'm his son, Masahiko.
我是他兒子真彥
So you're Matchy.
那不就跟阿真同名嘛
Hey, Junko,
我問你喔，純子
would you like to watch your father at work?
要不要參觀一下你爸爸的工作？
Sure.
好
You're so late, Ogawa.
你太晚來了啦，小川
I had to come because I was so worried.
我很擔心，所以來替你加油了
You should focus on that script instead.
那種事怎樣都好 快點寫連續劇的劇本啦
Mr. Ogawa, today you'll be competing in pairs.
小川先生，今天是兩人一組對戰
This is your partner.
這位是你今天的搭檔
I'm Yuki Matsumura.
我是松村雄基
What?! The Baddest Punk in Kawahama?
什麼？是川濱第一的不良少年耶
My goodness! It's him in the flesh!
天啊！是本人耶！
This is his daughter.
這位是他女兒
Can she stay to watch? She'll be quiet.
可以讓她觀摩嗎？她會乖乖的
Yes, sure.
好啊，可以
-You're going to appear on TV? -Yeah.
-老爸，你要上電視？ -對
Where's Aesop? Isn't he with you?
天哪，伊索沒有跟你一起來嗎？
Junko.
純子
I'm a big fan!
你演出的我都有看！
Welcome to General Knowledge Quiz,
《常識問答，令和Z世代 對上昭和老爸世代》
Let's dive straight into the first round!
馬上進行第一組的對戰
Representing Team Reiwa, we have the popular TikTokers, Potemkins!
令和隊是人氣TikTok主播 波邱姆金茲的兩人！
-Make sure to follow us!
-請追蹤我們！
On the opposing side, representing Team Showa,
對戰的昭和隊是演員松村雄基先生
Good to be here.
請多指教
According to our notes, Mr. Ogawa is EBS TV's counselor.
根據資料
Is your job hard?
工作很累人吧？
Oh, yeah.
是啊
The TV station is filled with cuckoos.
畢竟在電視台裡的 都是些腦袋不正常的人
Thank goodness this isn't live.
幸好不是現場直播
Let's kick off with the first question.
-進行第一題吧 -是
Team Showa, it's your turn.
請昭和隊回答
Insta…
Insta…
-Sapporo Ichiban! -No.
-札幌一番！ -不是…
-Instant noodles… -Sapporo Ichiban!
-不是在講泡麵… -札幌一番！
-Miso!
-並非泡麵… -味噌！
-Soy sauce! -Don't hit the table.
-醬油！ -不用拼命拍桌子
This isn't a buzzer quiz. Please calm down.
還有這不是搶答，請冷靜點
Listen carefully. Here goes.
請仔細聽題目，要說囉
Instagram offers a feature where you can share posts for 24 hours…
Instagram的功能中 24小時內的照片或影片會…
Stories.
限時動態？
Correct.
正確答案
Yeah!
好耶！
However,
但是呢
due to Mr. Ogawa's incorrect response, you don't earn any points.
因為小川先生搞砸了，所以沒得分
-My bad. -No worries.
-真抱歉 -別介意啦
Now, on to the next question.
接著是第二題
What is the name of this idol group?
這團體的名字是？
I can't answer this one. They all seem identical to me.
我回答不出來，看起來全都一樣
Thirty-eight!
38人！
You startled me!
嚇我一跳！
No, I didn't ask how many.
不對，那是人數吧
-Good effort on the counting, but-- -Onyanko, right?
-雖然你數得很快… -小貓俱樂部？
I know! It's School Mates!
我知道了！School Mates！
That's old. That's ancient.
-太老了 -那是什麼？
I'll give you a hint.
給你一個提示
Hills.
“坂道”
Hill start!
坂道出發！
-Wrong! -Hills.
-答錯了！ -坂道
There's no group by that name.
沒有那種團體吧
Minato ward! Many slopes--
港區很多坂道…
It's starting to look like the Elderly Buzzer Quiz.
像是在看《日本長壽老人搶答賽》
Unfortunately, no points for you this round!
很可惜，沒拿到分數
Now, it's Team Reiwa's turn.
接著進行令和隊的題目
-Yeah.
-來吧
This question is relevant to today's guest, Mr. Yuki Matsumura.
和今天的來賓松村雄基先生有關的
It's about the Showa era's delinquent culture.
昭和不良文化
A group attacking a delinquent on their way to school,
上學途中被一群不良少年攻擊
trying to steal their unique pants.
身上穿著的特殊長褲被搶走了
This was known as "something" hunting.
這叫做“狩獵”什麼？
-I have no idea. -Now,
-我不知道啦 -請回答
what is the name of this activity?
是“狩獵”什麼？
Geezer hunting!
狩獵大叔！
That's it!
就是那個！
Right?
是這個對吧？
Today, Mr. Ogawa has come wearing the special pants in question.
今天小川先生穿了這種長褲
-Let's take a look. -Okay.
-我們來看看吧 -好
Check this out.
就是這件
-What's he got on? -So lame!
-那是什麼？ -好土！
I've never seen anything like it!
我沒看過！
Is that a hakama?
根本是袴嘛
Festive season vibes.
值得慶祝的節日才要穿啦
Okay, time's up!
好，時間到！
The answer is bontan hunting!
正確答案是“狩獵燈籠褲”！
Who'd want to wear pants that lame, anyway?
話說誰想穿這種老土的褲子？
These aren't pants. They're called bontan.
這不是一般褲子，是燈籠褲
I wasn't asking you, Mr. Ogawa.
我沒在問小川先生啦
They might seem uncool now, but punks used to be proud of them.
這雖然很土 但可說是不良少年的門面
Back then, it was all about who had the puffiest pants.
當時大家會競爭褲管有多寬
Like mounting?
藉此展現“優越感”？
Mounting? What's that?
山？那是什麼？
Like climbing a mountain?
山脈嗎？
You're getting it wrong.
-發音不一樣啦 -不是山啊
We're not even in the same book.
雞同鴨講
It shows how times have changed.
因為時代差異
Anyway, neither team scored any points.
兩者都沒有得分
-All right, moving on-- -Hey.
-接著進行下一題… -喂
What was that, huh?
剛才那是怎樣？
Junko!
純子！
You should listen to my old man.
好好聽我老爸說話啊
You've been showing a bias toward the younger folks
從剛才就一直偏袒年輕人
and making fun of my dad.
瞧不起別人的老爸
Apologize.
給我道歉
It's rude.
很沒禮貌耶
I'm just following the script here…
但我只是按照劇本進行…
Miss, that's the nature of this show.
這位妹妹，本來就是這種節目啦
Huh? What kind of show is that?
什麼？哪種節目？
It's a show that pokes fun at our dads' generation
就是一邊嘲笑過時的老爸們
and teases the youths' ignorance,
同時也嘲笑年輕世代的無知
while also educating and fostering mutual understanding.
認識雙方的文化，並深度學習
-And updating old perspectives. -I don't get it.
-藉以更新老舊的價值觀 -搞不懂
You're turning him into a joke. Give me a break.
簡單來說就是公然嘲笑別人吧 少開玩笑了
The only one allowed to mock my dad
能嘲笑我老爸的
is me, his daughter.
就只有我這個女兒啦
Junko.
純子
If you're going to mock him, at least make it amusing.
既然要拿他當笑柄就做得有趣點啊
This isn't cutting it. It's not funny at all.
我笑不出來，一點意思也沒有
Is this all you've come up with after 38 years?
都過了38年，還是這種程度？
That's enough, Junko. Thank you.
已經夠了，純子，謝謝你
Don't touch me. I'm not doing this for you, geezer.
放開我，我又不是為了你這老頭
If you're the Baddest Punk in Kawahama, say something!
還有你也是
That drama aired 40 years ago.
那可是我40年前拍的連續劇啊
I just watched it the other day.
但我前陣子才看
It moved me and made me cry.
我還感動到哭
You're only 17.
因為你才17歲
That's why you take things so seriously.
所以才會認真看待這一切
Isn't that right? That's how we all were when we were 17.
編劇老師，你說是吧？ 我們17歲時都是這樣
We can't tell apart today's idols.
雖然我分不出現在的偶像
But we know Agnes Lum's BWH.
但說起安格妮絲林的三圍…
They're 90, 55, 92!
90、55、92！
We remember that, don't we?
就記得很牢，對吧？
Seventeen
17歲
The drama we were into was Yusaku's
我著迷的連續劇是優作的
Detective Story
《偵探物語》
We wanted a Vespa
想買一台偉士牌的機車
And delivered newspapers
所以去送報紙
Kudo, you don't know?
你不知道工藤嗎？
You're behind.
那就落伍了
We're not dwelling on the past
這不是在話當年
We're just talking
我們就只是在聊
About the time we were 17
17歲時的回憶
Seventeen
17歲
I was into Mr. Emoken's drama
我著迷的連續劇是江賢先生寫的作品
The one in which street gangs
在某個車站前
Hang around some station
有街頭幫派聚集的那齣
We're not dwelling on the past
這不是在話當年
We're just talking
我們就只是在聊
About the time we were 17
17歲時的回憶
Seventeen
17歲
I had already made my debut As a child actor
我當時已經以演員的身分出道
Ms. Mariko Kaga
加賀真理子小姐
Took good care of me
非常照顧我
Who cares?
誰在乎啊
I wasn't even born
我們又還沒出生
And yet, even you will age
然而你們總有一天也會老啊
Even TikTok will eventually
TikTok終有一日
Become a thing of the past
會變成過去的話題
Older men
叔叔
Older women
還有阿姨
Talk about the past
他們會忍不住開始話當年
Because they want
只是因為
To return to when they were 17
想要回到17歲
Older men
叔叔
Older women
還有阿姨
Talk about the past
他們會忍不住開始話當年
Because they can't
只是因為
Return to when they were 17
回不去17歲了
I am now
而我如今是
Seventeen
17歲
I'm not anyone
還沒成就
Yet
什麼大事
I'm still
我現在還只是
Seventeen
17歲
I don't have anything
還沒有當年的
To reminisce about
往事可以提
Junko.
純子
But this sight I'm seeing right now
但我現在看到的景象
will become a memory I can reminisce about.
有一天也會變成過去吧
Just kidding.
我只是說說啦
What were you like when you were 17?
小川先生17歲時是怎麼樣的感覺？
Me?
我嗎？
When I was 17, TV didn't exist.
17歲時還沒有電視呢
-Huh? -Yeah.
-什麼？ -真的啦
So, it was all about movies and the radio.
所以主要是看電影和聽廣播
Hey.
我問你
Where did Junko go?
純子去哪了？
Hey, did she turn into a frog?
回答啊，她變成青蛙了嗎？
Lady.
這位姐姐
Middle-aged lady!
這位媽媽！
-Old lady! -Shut up!
-這位阿姨！ -吵死了！
I'm trying to focus.
我現在得專心
Moving on, we'll read another postcard.
那麼，介紹下一張明信片
The handle is Mysterious Transfer Student.
筆名為神祕轉學生
-"Hello, Yuri." -Can I have a soda float?
-“你好，悠里先生” -老闆，一杯冰淇淋汽水
Okay.
好
"There's a student in my class I haven't met yet."
“班上有一位從沒見過的同學”
Huh?
什麼？
"There was a time when I couldn't attend junior high school either,
“我在國中時也有一段時間無法上學
so I want to be there for S as well."
為了成為S同學聊天的對象
"That's why I've sent postcards to a lot of shows."
才像這樣投稿明信片到各廣播節目
"S, if you're listening to this, please reply."
S同學，如果你聽到了 請回覆我吧”
Sorry for coming over so many times, I…
抱歉多次打擾，我…
Come in.
請進
Thanks.
打擾了
There you are!
找到了！
Nagisa!
小渚…
Check it out! Mr. Emo submitted the title and plot of the story.
來了！我收到了江面先生 寫的劇名和故事大綱
That's amazing! What did you think?
太好了！內容怎麼樣？
I haven't read it yet.
-我還沒讀 -什麼？
"Seventeen."
《17歲，永不忘卻這景象》
It's a school drama.
是校園劇嘛
I'm so excited, I feel sick!
好興奮，我快吐了！
But what if it sucks?
不過如果很沒意思怎麼辦？
There's no way it could be bad.
怎麼可能會無聊嘛
You're right. Emoken is the embodiment of our youth!
也對，江賢就是我們的青春嘛！
Thanks.
謝謝
-Coffee, please. -Just a moment.
-請給我咖啡 -好
Nagisa, so you have a kid?
渚小姐，聽說你有小孩？
Huh?
什麼？
My dad told me.
我聽老爸說的
I'm impressed.
不敢置信
You don't look like it at all.
看起來完全不像有孩子
Thanks.
謝謝
Where's your husband?
你先生呢？
We couldn't see eye to eye, so we recently split up.
我跟他不合，所以不久前離婚了
You're cool for working so hard.
看你這麼有幹勁地工作，真帥氣
I respect you.
我好尊敬你
Say, Junko.
我問你喔，純子
Do you like kids?
你喜歡小孩嗎？
Sure.
當然
I love them!
最喜歡了
Yeah?
這樣啊
Hey, after we're done,
我們吃完這些後
let's go clothes shopping.
要不要去買衣服？
Huh?
什麼？
I want to buy you some clothes.
我想送你衣服當禮物
Let's go to Harajuku.
我們去原宿吧
Okay.
好啊
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻譯：黃琴喻
Do they have to be resolved?
不得不收回來？
They do. I'm a perfectionist.
對，我是完美主義者
-The deadline! -I'm Naoki, I'll cut your hair.
-截稿日！ -我是今天的設計師，直樹
I want to show you all the sights I know.
我想帶你去能看到美景的所有地方
Where did Junko go?
純子去哪了？
-I might stay over. -You can't!
-可能會過夜 -絕對不行！
-I like him. -You've got to be kidding.
-很喜歡喔 -不會吧
The last episode is undecided?
最後一集竟然還沒確定
That's awesome!
那不是很棒嗎？